Guide to the Refugee Lives Oral History Project, 2015-2018 RL.11095
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Refugee Lives Oral History Project
2015-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kalow, Nancy
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
RL.11095
604 Files Electronic documents, including Microsoft Word files, JPG files, MP3 files, Apple MOV files, MP4 files, M4A files, and Adobe PDF files.
18.02 Gigabytes
Oral histories, transcriptions, videos, and fieldnotes created by students in Doc Studies 321S-01/ AMES 320S at Duke University/Center for Documentary Studies, 2015-2018. The courses were facilitated by CDS Faculty member Nancy Kalow, AMES faculty member miriam cooke, and AMES faculty member Maha Houssami.
Arrangement
Chronological by year, alphabetical by name.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Refugee Lives Oral History Project was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015, 2017, and 2018.
Collection Overview
For the spring semester 2015, Nancy Kalow, Maha Houssami, and miriam cooke were awarded an Innovation & Entrepreneurship Course Innovation Grant for AMES 320S: Refugee Lives. In this course, eleven undergraduates conducted oral history interviews with local refugee families from Iraq and Sudan. The AMES 320S final documentary projects were posted on Duke's Languages in Durham website and shared during Middle East Refugee Awareness Week in April 2015 that was dedicated to the life and work of Deah Barakat, Yusor Abu Salha and Razan Abu Salha, the three Muslim students murdered in Chapel Hill in February 2015. In the Spring 2016 AMES 320S: Refugee Lives course, students carried out interviews with refugees and asylees from Syria, Sudan, and Iraq. Syrian refugees, Ghoson and Ammar, are residing in Paris and Syrian refugee Sanaa Domat resides in Montreal. Sudanese refugee Hamid Bejeen resides in North Carolina. Iraqi refugees Fanar Al-Badwani, Suhama Ali (known as Um Mustafa), Hanaa Aljashamy (known as Um Bashar), Sarah Bashi, Suzan Gwarges, Sahlam Hasan, and Jaffar Lani reside in North Carolina. Iraqi asylee Abdul Sattar Jawad resides in North Carolina. Interviews with Sanaa Domat, Ghoson, and Ammar were conducted by Skype or telephone. The other interviews were recorded in person. The Skype interview with Ghoson was done in Arabic by Refugee Lives instructor Maha Houssami during class; English interpretation by Maha. The interview with Hamid Bejeen was done in Arabic and was partially translated by the student interviewers. The other eight interviews were in English. Some of these materials appear in public-facing edited versions on Duke Service-Learning's Arabic Communities website. In the Spring 2017 AMES 320S: Refugee Lives course, eighteen undergraduates conducted oral history interviews via Skype with Syrian refugees now residing in Canada, Brazil, Lebanon, Germany, and Italy. To support undergraduate documentary research, Nancy Kalow and Maha Houssami were awarded two grants: a David Paletz Innovative Teaching award and an award from the Vice Provost for the Arts. The AMES 320S final documentary projects were posted on Duke's Languages in Durham website: https://sites.duke.edu/arabiccommunities/stories/syria/. The final projects consist of a four-minute audio documentary, edited from the three long-form oral history interviews, along with an image chosen by the refugee interview partner, a transcript of the four-minute piece, and a brief written introduction by the student team who carried out the interviews. All interviews were conducted in English. For the Spring 2018 AMES 320S: Refugee Lives class, students worked in groups of two and three to carry out oral history interviews with refugees from Syria and Iraq. The Syrian refugees were residing in Erbil (Iraq), Greece, and Germany, and the Iraqi refugee was currently residing in Turkey. Interviews were conducted by Skype and recorded on wav files. Two interviews of approximately one hour duration were recorded over the semesters with each refugee. Interviews were in English, and students transcribed the audio and wrote fieldnotes. The public-facing edited versions (approximately four minutes each) of the interviews were posted on Duke Service-Learning's Arabic Communities website.
Audiovisual materials; Oral history interviews; Refugees -- Sudan; Refugees -- Iraq; Refugees -- Syria
- 2015 Interviews
  Scope and Contents
  For the spring semester 2015, Nancy Kalow, Maha Houssami, and miriam cooke were awarded an Innovation & Entrepreneurship Course Innovation Grant for AMES 320S: Refugee Lives. In this course, eleven undergraduates conducted oral history interviews with local refugee families from Iraq and Sudan. The AMES 320S final documentary projects were posted on Duke's Languages in Durham website and shared during Middle East Refugee Awareness Week in April 2015 that was dedicated to the life and work of Deah Barakat, Yusor Abu Salha and Razan Abu Salha, the three Muslim students murdered in Chapel Hill in February 2015.
  - Adam, Saad Omar, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Adam, Saad Omar)
  - Daud, Bakhit Fadul, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Daud, Bakhit Fadul)
  - Ghofran, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Ghofran)
  - Laith, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Laith)
  - Sufyaan, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Sufyaan)
  - Yakob, Mohamed, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Yakob, Mohamed)
  - Course materials, 2015 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Course materials)
- 2016 Interviews
  In the Spring 2016 AMES 320S: Refugee Lives course, students carried out interviews with refugees and asylees from Syria, Sudan, and Iraq. Syrian refugees, Ghoson and Ammar, are residing in Paris and Syrian refugee Sanaa Domat resides in Montreal. Sudanese refugee Hamid Bejeen resides in North Carolina. Iraqi refugees Fanar Al-Badwani, Suhama Ali (known as Um Mustafa), Hanaa Aljashamy (known as Um Bashar), Sarah Bashi, Suzan Gwarges, Sahlam Hasan, and Jaffar Lani reside in North Carolina. Iraqi asylee Abdul Sattar Jawad resides in North Carolina. Interviews with Sanaa Domat, Ghoson, and Ammar were conducted by Skype or telephone. The other interviews were recorded in person. The Skype interview with Ghoson was done in Arabic by Refugee Lives instructor Maha Houssami during class; English interpretation by Maha. The interview with Hamid Bejeen was done in Arabic and was partially translated by the student interviewers. The other eight interviews were in English. Some of these materials appear in public-facing edited versions on Duke Service-Learning's Arabic Communities website.
  - Al-Badwani, Fanar, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Al-Badwani, Fanar)
  - Ali, Suhama (Um Mustafa), 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Ali, Suhama (Um Mustafa))
  - Aljashamy, Hanaa (Um Bashar), 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Aljashamy, Hanaa (Um Bashar))
  - Ammar, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Ammar)
  - Bashi, Sarah, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Bashi, Sarah)
  - Bejeen, Hamid, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Bejeen, Hamid)
  - Domat, Sanaa, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Domat, Sanaa)
  - Ghoson, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Ghoson)
  - Gwarges, Suzan, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Gwarges, Suzan)
  - Hasan, Sahlam, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Hasan, Sahlam)
  - Jawad, Abdul Sattar, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Jawad, Abdul Sattar)
  - Lani, Jaffar, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0002, E-folder Lani, Jaffar)
  - Course materials, 2016 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0001, E-folder Course materials)
- 2017 Interviews
  In the Spring 2017 AMES 320S: Refugee Lives course, eighteen undergraduates conducted oral history interviews via Skype with Syrian refugees now residing in Canada, Brazil, Lebanon, Germany, and Italy. To support undergraduate documentary research, Nancy Kalow and Maha Houssami were awarded two grants: a David Paletz Innovative Teaching award and an award from the Vice Provost for the Arts. The AMES 320S final documentary projects were posted on Duke's Languages in Durham website: https://sites.duke.edu/arabiccommunities/stories/syria/. The final projects consist of a four-minute audio documentary, edited from the three long-form oral history interviews, along with an image chosen by the refugee interview partner, a transcript of the four-minute piece, and a brief written introduction by the student team who carried out the interviews. All interviews were conducted in English.
  - Alaktaa, Saeed, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder Alaktaa, Saeed)
  - Alaziz, Ghayath Abd, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder Alaziz, Ghayath Abd)
  - K, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder K)
  - Kouja, Abdulkader, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder Kouja, Abdulkader)
  - Omr, Carmen, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder Omr, Carmen)
  - Shanko, Gueya, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder Shanko, Gueya)
  - Course materials, 2017 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0003, E-folder Course materials)
- 2018 Interviews
  For the Spring 2018 AMES 320S: Refugee Lives class, students worked in groups of two and three to carry out oral history interviews with refugees from Syria and Iraq. The Syrian refugees were residing in Erbil (Iraq), Greece, and Germany, and the Iraqi refugee was currently residing in Turkey. Interviews were conducted by Skype and recorded on wav files. Two interviews of approximately one hour duration were recorded over the semesters with each refugee. Interviews were in English, and students transcribed the audio and wrote fieldnotes. Two of the interviewees wished to be known by their first name only (Mahmoud) or by an initial (T). The interviews were open-ended and relationship-based, with the refugee directing the conversation if they chose to. Students avoided topics that the refugee wanted to avoid, such as T not wanting to share her story of why she had to leave Iraq. The public-facing edited versions (approximately four minutes each) of the interviews were posted on Duke Service-Learning's Arabic Communities website.
  - Ahmed, Hadiya, 2018 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0004, E-folder Ahmed, Hadiya)
  - Khaled, Shadi, 2018 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0004, E-folder Khaled, Shadi)
  - Mahmoud, 2018 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0004, E-folder Mahmoud)
  - T, 2018 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0004, E-folder T)
  - Zedin, Jan, 2018 (Digital-materials RL11095-SET-0004, E-folder Zedin, Jan)